<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic id="template_id">
  <title>SD Memory Cards</title>
  <prolog>
    <author>Matthew Schinkel</author>
    <publisher>Jallib Group</publisher>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p id="firstcontent">In this tuturial we will learn how to use an SD Card for data storage</p>
    <section>
      <title>Some SD Card info:</title>
      <p>SD Cards are quite popular these days for things like digital camera&apos;s, video camera&apos;s, mp3 players and mobile phones. The main advantages are: small size, large data storage capability, speed, cost and flash data storage that does not require power to hold data. The current version of the sd card library works with &quot;standard capacity&quot; sd cards up  4gb in size.</p>
      <image href="images/sd_card_sd_card.jpg" width="250"/>
      <image href="images/sd_card_pinout.jpg" width="300"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Let&apos;s put one in our circuit!</title>
      <p>With the use of the sd card lib (sd_card.jal) and a sample file 16f877_sd_card.jal, we can easily put one in our own circuit for mass data storage! </p>
      <p>SD Card have 2 data transfer types &quot;sd bus&quot; and &quot;spi bus&quot;. Most PIC&apos;s have an SPI port.  The &quot;sd bus&quot; is faster but uses more pins. As you can see from the circuit we are using SPI.</p>
      <p>These SD Cards are 3.3v devices, therefore a 5v to 3v conversion is needed between the PIC and the sd card. We will use resistors to do the conversion, however there are many other methods. See <xref href="http://www.microchip.com/3v/" format="html">http://www.microchip.com/3v/</xref> for more information. Another setup may be needed if you are putting more devices on the same SPI bus.</p>
      <p>Let&apos;s build the circuit:</p>
      <image href="images/sd_card_schematic.jpg" width="500" otherprops="clickable"/>
      <title>Power It Up</title>
      <p>Now that our circuit is built, lets test it and make sure it works before we continue with more details. Compile and program your pic with 16f877_sd_card.jal from your jallib samples directory and. plug your circuit into your PC for serial port communication and apply 5v power. After pressing the reset button, you should get a result similar to this:</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
