<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic-1">
  <title>PWM (Part 2) - Sound and Frequency with Piezo Buzzer</title>
  <prolog>
    <author>Sébastien Lelong</author>
    <publisher>Jallib Group</publisher>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>In <xref href="tutorial_pwm1.xml">previous tutorial</xref>, we had fun by controlling the brightness of a LED, using PWM. This time, we&apos;re going to have even more fun with a <i>piezo buzzer</i>, or a small <i>speaker</i>.</p>
    <p>If you <xref href="tutorial_pwm_intro.xml">remember</xref>, with PWM, you can either vary the <b>duty cycle</b> or the <b>frequency</b>. Controlling the brightness of a LED, ie. produce a variable voltage on the average, can be done by having a <i>constant frequency</i> (high enough) and <i>vary the duty cycle</i>. This time, this will be the opposite: we&apos;ll have a constant duty cycle, and vary the frequency.</p>
    <section>
      <title>What is a piezo buzzer ? </title>
      <p>It&apos;s a &quot;component&quot; with a material having <i>piezoelectric</i> ability. <xref href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piezoelectricity" format="html">Piezoelectricity</xref> is the ability for a material to produce voltage when it get distorted. The reverse is also true: <i>when you produce a voltage, the material gets distorted</i>. When you stop producing a voltage, it gets back to its original shape. If you&apos;re fast enough with this on/off voltage setting, then <i>the piezo will start to oscillate</i>, and will <b>produce sound</b>. How sweet...</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Constant duty cycle ? Why ?</title>
      <p>So we now know why we need to vary the frequency. This will make the piezo oscillates more and less, and produces sounds at different levels. If you produce a 440Hz frequency, you&apos;ll get a nice <xref href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A440" format="html">A3</xref>.</p>
      <p>But why having a <i>constant duty cycle</i> ? What is the role of the duty cycle in this case ? Remember: when making a piezo oscillate, it&apos;s not the amount of volts which is important, it&apos;s how you turn the voltage on/off<fn>I guess this is about energy or something like that. One guru could explain the maths here...</fn>:<ul>
          <li><b>when setting the duty cycle to 10%</b>: during a period, piezo will get distorted 10% on the time, and remain inactive 90% on the time. <i>The oscillation proportion is low</i>.</li>
          <li><b>when setting the duty cycle to 50%</b>: the piezo is half distorted, half inactive. The <i>oscillation proportion is high</i>, because the piezo oscillates at the its maximal amplitude, it&apos;s half and equally distorted and inactive.</li>
          <li><b>when setting the duty cycle to 90%</b>: the piezo will get distorted during 90% of a period, then nothing. The <i>oscillation proportion is low again</i>, because the proportion between distortion and inactivity is not equal. </li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>So, to summary, what is the purpose of the duty cycle in our case ? The <b>volume</b> ! You can vary the volume of the sound by modifying the duty cycle. 0% will produce no sounds, 50% will be the max volume. Between 50% and 100% is the same as between 0% and 50%. So, when I say when need a constant duty cycle, it&apos;s not that true, it&apos;s just that we&apos;ll set it at 50%, so the chances we hear something are high :)</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Let&apos;s produce sounds ! </title>
      <p>The schematics will use is exactly the same as on the previous post with the LED, except the LED is replaced with a piezo buzzer, like this:</p>
      <image href="images/pwm_sound.jpg" placement="break"/>
      <image href="images/pwm_sound_piezo.jpg" placement="break"/>
      <p>By the way, how to observe the &quot;duty cycle effect&quot; on the volume ? Just program your PIC with the previous experiment one, which control the brightness of a LED, and power on the circuit. I wanted to show a video with sounds, but the frequency is too high, my camera can&apos;t record it...</p>
      <p>Anyway, that&apos;s a little bit boring, we do want sounds...
</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Writing the software</title>
      <p>The software part has a lot of similarities with the <xref href="tutorial_pwm1.xml">previous experiment</xref>. The initialization is the same, I let you have a look. Only the <codeph>forever loop</codeph> has changed:<codeblock>var dword counter = 0
forever loop

  for 100_000 using counter loop
     pwm_set_frequency(counter)
     -- Setting @50% gives max volume
     -- must be re-computed each time the frequency
     -- changes, because it depends on PR2 value
     pwm1_set_percent_dutycycle(50)
  end loop

end loop</codeblock></p>
      <p>
Quite straightforward:<ul>
          <li>we &quot;explore&quot; frequencies between 0 and 100 000 Hz, using a <codeph>counter</codeph></li>
          <li>we use <codeph>pwm_set_frequency(counter)</codeph> to set the frequency, in Hertz. It takes a dword as parameter (ie. you can explore a lot of frequencies...)</li>
          <li>finally, as we want a 50% duty cycle, and since its value is different for each frequency setting, we need to re-compute it on each loop.</li>
        </ul><note>jallib&apos;s PWM libraries are coming from a &quot;heavy refactoring&quot; of Guru Stef Mientki&apos;s PWM library. While integrating it to jallib, we&apos;ve modified the library so frequencies can be set and changed during program execution. This wasn&apos;t the case before, because the frequency was set as a constant.</note></p>
      <p>So, how does this look like ? Hope you&apos;ll like the sweet melody :)</p>
      <p><xref href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xZ9OhQUKGtQ" format="html">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xZ9OhQUKGtQ</xref></p>
      <p>
        <object width="480" height="385">
            <param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/xZ9OhQUKGtQ"></param>
            <param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"></param>
            <param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"></param>
        </object>
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>&quot;Where can I download the files ?&quot;</title>
      <p>As usual, you&apos;ll need the <xref href="http://code.google.com/p/jallib/downloads/list" format="html">latest jallib pack</xref> (at least 0.2 version). You&apos;ll also find the exact code we used <xref href="http://code.google.com/p/jallib/source/browse/trunk/doc/dita/tutorials/code/blog_16f88_pwm_sound.jal" format="jal">here</xref>.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
