<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
"topic.dtd">
<topic id="template_id">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <prolog>
    <author>Jallib Group</author>

    <publisher>Jallib Group</publisher>
  </prolog>

  <body>
    <p id="firstcontent_1">JALv2 &amp; Jallib installation guide</p>

    <section id="getting_1"><title>Getting Jallib</title><p>The Jallib
    repository is maintained at <xref format="html"
    href="http://justanotherlanguage.org/downloads"
    scope="external">http://justanotherlanguage.org/downloads</xref>. It's
    safer to ignore the "<i>Automated weekly build...</i>" files in this
    download directory (these, as the prefix implies, are updates to the
    repository automatically compiled by the server and are probably
    untested). Look instead for the latest version of the release file which
    has the annotation "<i>Don't know which to choose? Take this one!</i>".
    These are the tested releases and, while we can't guarantee that there
    won't be any bugs at all, will provide a reasonably trouble-free
    installation.</p><p>The release files are all ZIP archives, which can be
    easily unpacked on most modern operating systems (Windows/Linux/MacOSX).
    Jallib releases also all come complete with a pre-compiled binary version
    of the JALv2 compiler for both Windows and Linux in the top-level
    <i>compiler</i> directory and a full set of documentation (including a
    copy of this tutorial) in the top-level <i>doc</i> directory, so there's
    nothing to stop you getting started straight away.</p></section>

    <section><title>Windows Install:</title><ol>
        <li>Download the latest stable Jallib release installer executable
        from <xref format="html"
        href="http://justanotherlanguage.org/downloads"
        scope="external">http://justanotherlanguage.org/downloads</xref>, This
        will install JALv2 + JalEdit</li>

        <li>Update your installation (very important) - Download jallib-pack
        or jallib-pack-bee from <xref format="html"
        href="http://justanotherlanguage.org/downloads"
        scope="external">http://justanotherlanguage.org/downloads</xref>, copy
        the .zip contents into your Jallib installation directory.</li>

        <li>Run the setup file</li>

        <li>Run JalEdit.exe from the "jaledit" directory</li>

        <li>(optional) Click Tools Menu -&gt; Environment Options -&gt;
        Programmer, Then Set the Programmer Executable Path</li>
      </ol><p>You should see something like this under Windows:</p> <image
    href="images/installation_jalv2_dir.jpg"/></section>

    <section><title>Linux Install</title><note>All instances of filenames or
    paths within square brackets below (eg:-
    <cmdname>[filename.tar.gz]</cmdname>) are for illustration only. You will
    need to change these examples to suit your specific installation. Do
    <b>not</b> just copy and paste the examples!</note><note>Two commands
    (<cmdname>tar/unzip</cmdname>) are shown below for unpacking the Jallib
    file. You only need to use one or the other, not both. Which one you use
    depends upon the suffix of the file. If the filename ends in ".tar.gz",
    use the <cmdname>tar</cmdname> command. If the filename ends in ".zip",
    use the <cmdname>unzip</cmdname> command.</note><ol>
        <li>Go to <xref format="html"
        href="http://justanotherlanguage.org/downloads"
        scope="external">http://justanotherlanguage.org/downloads</xref> and
        select the link for the latest, stable version of Jallib (see:-
        Getting Jallib, above)</li>

        <li>Change directory ("<cmdname>cd [/target/directory]</cmdname>") to
        the location where you intend to install JALv2</li>

        <li>Download the zip-file of the stable Jallib release. </li>

        <li>unzip the package with: <cmdname>$ unzip
        [filename.zip]</cmdname></li>
      </ol><p>You should see something like this under Linux:</p> <image
    href="images/installation_jalv2_dir_linux.jpg"/> <note>Jaledit also runs
    under Wine on Linux</note></section>
  </body>
</topic>
