<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
"topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic-1">
  <title>Building a serial port board with the max232 device</title>

  <prolog>
    <author>Matthew Schinkel</author>

    <publisher>Jallib Group</publisher>
  </prolog>

  <body>
    <p>In this tutorial, we're going to build a serial port that can connect
    your PIC's TX and RX pins to your pc or other hardware using a max232
    chip.</p>

    <section><p>Many circuits will require some serial port communication, you
    may buy yourself a rs232 to TTL adapter off the net for as little as $10,
    or you can build one yourself. The max232 is a very popular chip. It
    converts your 5v circuit to the 12v required for serial communication to
    things like your PC. Many microcontrollers have RX and TX output pins.
    Here is a image of the max232 adapter I purchased. It has input pins for
    RX, TX, CT, RT as well as GND and 5v. The RX and TX pins can be directly
    connected to your PIC.</p><p><image
    href="images/serialboard_purchased1.jpg" otherprops="clickable"
    width="150"/><image href="images/serialboard_purchased2.jpg"
    otherprops="clickable" width="150"/><image
    href="images/serialboard_purchased3.jpg" otherprops="clickable"
    width="150"/></p></section>

    <section><p><b>Now, lets build our own! </b></p><p>First get yourself a
    RS232 port, you can cut up one of your serial port cords, or buy a port
    from the store for a dollar or two. </p><p><image
    href="images/serialboard_port.jpg" width="200"/><image
    href="images/serialboard_port2.jpg" width="244"/></p></section>

    <section><p>I am going to use a cut serial port cord since it already has
    leads on it, and is long enough to reach my pc. Use your multi-meter to
    find the pin numbers, and touch up the wires with solder so they’ll go
    into your breadboard easily. </p><p>Now build the circuit, As you can see,
    you will need the max232 chip from your local electronics store and a few
    1uf capacitors. </p><p><image href="images/serialboard_max232.jpg"
    width="400"/></p><p><image href="images/serialboard_breadboard.jpg"
    width="400"/></p></section>

    <section><p>Great job, now connect the RX and TX pins to your circuit, and
    plug the rs232 port directly your pc, or to a usb-to-serial adapter, or
    even to a bluetooth-to-serial adapter for short range wireless.</p><p>I
    strongly suggest you make this on a PCB with pins that will plug to your
    breadboard. you’ll use it a lot!</p><p>In this image, I did not complete
    my PIC circuit, but I think you get the idea:</p><p><image
    href="images/serialboard_serial-board.jpg" width="400"/></p><p>You can use
    serial_hardware lib or serial_software lib to transmit data to your pc,
    check for it in the other jallib projects. I suggest the software realterm
    for sending/receiving data to your PIC</p><p>Open Source REALTERM
    http://realterm.sourceforge.net/ </p><p>It can be downloaded for free from
    http://sourceforge.net/projects/realterm/files/ </p><p>Open the software,
    click “Port”, choose your speed and port number and press
    “open”</p><p><b>Hex output</b></p><p><image
    href="images/serialboard_realterm.jpg" width="450"/></p><p><b>ASCII
    output</b></p><p><image href="images/serialboard_realterm2.jpg"
    width="450"/></p></section>
  </body>
</topic>
